A Guide to the Blanche Lemco van Ginkel Architectural Collection, 1956-2006, 2013
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Blanche Lemco van Ginkel Architectural Collection, 1956-2006, 2013
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1988-122
1 box, 0.2 cu. ft.
Blanche Lemco van Ginkel is a retired architect and Professor Emerita at the University of Toronto. The collection consists biographical information about van Ginkel and her career, some of her publications, professional project information, and articles and research materials about the history of women in architecture in Canada.
Blanche Lemco van Ginkel
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Blanche Lemco van Ginkel Architectural Collection was donated to the Special Collections by their creator in 1988 with additions in 1997, 2002, and 2006.
Biographical Information
Blanche Lemco van Ginkel was born in 1923. She graduated from McGill University in Canada with a Bachelor of Architecture in 1945 and from Harvard University with a Masters in City Planning in 1950.
She is a retired partner of the architectural firm of Van Ginkel Associates, Architects and Town Planners in Toronto, begun in 1957, as well as a Professor Emerita at the University of Toronto. In 1948 she worked with Le Corbusier in Paris before coming to the University of Pennsylvania in 1951-1957. Her work at Van Ginkel Associates includes designs for historic Bowring Park in St. John's, Newfoundland, the Port of Montreal, working as a consultant in Expo'67 Montreal as well as various residential and town planning projects in Canada and abroad.
Van Ginkel is a Fellow in the Royal Architectural Institute of Canada (FRAIC), a member of Ontario Association of Architects, a member of the Canadian Institute of Planners, an associate of the Royal institute of British Architects, a member of the Royal Canadian Academy of Arts, and an Honorary Fellow of the American Institute of Architects (Hon. FAIA). She was awarded an honorary doctorate by the University in Aix-Marseille in 2005. She is also a founding member and has served as an advisor to the International Archives of Women in Architecture (IAWA).
Scope and Content
The collection consists of biographical materials about van Ginkel and material she has written, her professional projects, and collected research about women in architecture. Personal information includes curriculum vitae, newspaper and magazine articles about her, some of her publications about architectural planning and women architects, and selected letters and speaking notes she made during the course of her career. These include speeches to professional organizations in which she is involved and her letter protesting the unequal pensions paid to female professors by the University of Toronto. Professional project information includes project bulletins from her firm. There is also a collection of research notes, papers, and exhibition notices about the history of women in architecture in Canada, some of which were compiled and written by Mary Clark.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by material type in the following order: biographical information and articles by and about van Ginkel, professional project work, and materials about Canadian women architects.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
More information about Blanche Lemco van Ginkel's architectural career is held in the collections of the archives at the Collection Centre Canadien d'Architecture-Canadian Centre for Architecture, Montreal (CCA) - it holds the administrative and project records of the firm Van Ginkel Associates, 1955-1980, Accession Number AR1988:0017.
Contents List
- Curriculum vitae and biographical information, 1987-2001 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Articles written about van Ginkel, 1956-2003, 2013 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Articles written by van Ginkel, 1961-1993 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Letters and speeches written by van Ginkel, 1972-2002 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Program and speeches from Honorary Doctorate ceremony in Aix, 2005 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Correspondence with Milka Bliznakov about women architects and IAWA, 1988-2006 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Plans for CIAM X project submission, 1956 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Project brochure, Montreal International Airport, 1968 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Project brochure, Beaver Hall Square, Reclaimed, 1971 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Press release materials for the exhibit For the Record: Ontario Women Graduates in Architecture, 1920-1960, organized by Mary Clark, 1986 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Paper, Women Graduates in Architecture from Canadian Universities, with preliminary overview written by Mary Clark of University of Toronto, 1988 (Box-folder 1:11)
- Paper, Registration of Women Architects in Canada and survey results, written by Mary Clark of University of Toronto, 1988 (Box-folder 1:12)
- Biographical information on University of Toronto women graduates in architecture from 1920-1960 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Alice Ayer Alison
  - Dama Lumly Bell
  - Joan Burt
  - Phyllis Cook Carlisle
  - Audrey Koehler Christie
  - Margaret Gisborne Christie
  - Mary Patterson Clark
  - Beatrice Centner Davidson
  - Margaret Synge Dryer
  - Lennox Grafton
  - Joan Robinson Grierson
  - Jean Hall
  - Elizabeth Lalor Harding
  - Katharine Jefferys Helm
  - Marjorie Hill
  - Mary Imrie
  - Kathleen Connor Irvine
  - Martha Stewart Leitch
  - Natalie Salkauskis Liacas
  - Ann Gauthier Malott
  - Monica Nomberg
  - Joanna Barclay de Tolly Ozdowski
  - Ruthetta Kaplan Reiss
  - Shelagh Macdonnell Rounthwaite
  - Marjorie Sewell Shepland
  - Catherine Currie Smale
  - Isobel Grace Stewart
  - Jean Taylor Strange
- Research and statistics about women architects in Canada, ca 1985-1997 (Box-folder 1:14)
- Research notes on architect Marjorie Hill (Box-folder 1:15)